[
  {
    "question": "Pollen tube grows through the tissues of the ______ and style and reaches the ovary.",
    "answer": "stigma"
  },
  {
    "question": "In some plants, pollen grains are shed at ______-celled condition.",
    "answer": "two"
  },
  {
    "question": "In plants with two-celled pollen, the generative cell divides and forms the ______ male gametes during the growth of pollen tube.",
    "answer": "two"
  },
  {
    "question": "In plants which shed pollen in the three-celled condition, pollen tubes carry the ______ male gametes from the beginning.",
    "answer": "two"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pollen tube, after reaching the ovary, enters the ovule through the ______.",
    "answer": "micropyle"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pollen tube enters one of the synergids through the ______ apparatus.",
    "answer": "filiform"
  },
  {
    "question": "Filiform apparatus is present at the ______ part of the synergids.",
    "answer": "micropylar"
  },
  {
    "question": "Events from pollen deposition on the stigma until pollen tubes enter the ovule are called ______ interaction.",
    "answer": "pollen-pistil"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pollen-pistil interaction is a dynamic process involving pollen ______ followed by promotion or inhibition.",
    "answer": "recognition"
  },
  {
    "question": "Knowledge of pollen-pistil interaction helps plant breeders manipulate pollination even in ______ pollinations.",
    "answer": "incompatible"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pollen germination can be studied by dusting pollen on a glass slide containing about ______ per cent sugar solution.",
    "answer": "10"
  },
  {
    "question": "After about ______ minutes, pollen tubes can be observed coming out of pollen grains under a microscope.",
    "answer": "15â€“30"
  },
  {
    "question": "Artificial ______ is one of the major approaches of crop improvement programme.",
    "answer": "hybridisation"
  },
  {
    "question": "To ensure only desired pollen is used, the stigma is protected from contamination by ______ techniques.",
    "answer": "emasculation and bagging"
  },
  {
    "question": "Removal of anthers from the flower bud before anther dehiscence is called ______.",
    "answer": "emasculation"
  },
  {
    "question": "Emasculated flowers are covered with a bag generally made up of ______ paper.",
    "answer": "butter"
  },
  {
    "question": "Covering the flower to prevent contamination of its stigma is called ______.",
    "answer": "bagging"
  },
  {
    "question": "When stigma of a bagged flower attains ______, pollen from the male parent is dusted on it.",
    "answer": "receptivity"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the female parent produces ______ flowers, emasculation is not required.",
    "answer": "unisexual"
  },
  {
    "question": "Female flower buds are bagged before flowers ______ to prevent unwanted pollination.",
    "answer": "open"
  }
]
